Hey Kim, I'm going live. I need
my fangs. Have you seen them?
No, I haven't seen them.
Did you check the cupboard?
Yes, I checked the cupboard.
Here, just put this helmet on.
Kim, that's not even the
same character. I'm going to
be... Oh wait, we're live.
In three... Oh, we are live.
Welcome to Data 5300.
Oh well, that introduction seemed like
a good idea last night about midnight.
Moving on, Module 10, excited to
introduce you to date functions.
If you're taking the class fall
semester, it works perfectly for
the monster's theme that we have.
And if you're taking it spring
semester, well, we have some kind
of happy St. Patrick's Day monster.
On the screen, I'll provide the
login that you'll use for both
the blue triad and for your
lab. It differs from semester to
semester, so it'll show up on the
screen. And this will give you access
to the monster data set. And
then what we're going to do today
is I'm going to take you through
these various date functions.
As a reminder, they're called
functions because they have
the parentheses. And within
those parentheses, most
of the time, we'll include
arguments to those functions.
And so that is part of our task for
today. I also have a separate short
video on union and union all. We
introduced this topic briefly because
it's also now commonly asked in
interviews. originally it was only a
5310 topic but we're moving part
of relational database functions in
terms of unions so that'll be a very
short second video and then we have
one of my favorite animations which
covers the end of month and that
topic was important enough there are
several companies that hire many of
our students in every interview they
ask an end of month question so we
have a complete separate video animation
for that along with the animation
quiz it's kind of based on the
Back to the Future theme, so I hope
you really enjoy it. We'll go
ahead and start with the most basic
function for date functions, which would
be the year, the month, and the day
function. And this simply returns
the system date in date time format
related to the piece of the full
date that you would like, either the
year, the month, or the day. So
you have a chance to break down the
entire date. Now, your data set that
you'll use, I've provided the login.
you may have different columns but
you'll at least have one date column
and maybe more than one for the for
this demonstration we'll just use
the starting date column and then for
the lab you might have more columns
based on what we load into files it
changes from semester to semester
so I'll make this a little more
specific I'm just going to indicate
citing date from the monster sighting
and that gives us the year the
month and the day. And so in this
case, if we have a report that only
requires the month, which month
did, you know, this customer make a
purchase, then we can use the month
function and then include the column
with the date that we'd like to
parse out. And in this case, this
should return hopefully 10 or it
retrieves the month for each one. Now
you also would have to create an
alias for that. So this is the most
basic month, day, year. On smaller
data set, these date functions are
great and provide a lot of flexibility
on massive and large data sets.
They can cause problems with
performance in terms of query
tuning, and that's a topic that
we discuss later in the semester.
Let's go ahead and take a
look now at the second topic.
And as we go through this, we'll
start to add the different topics
that we're learning and add these
in this bottom left column. But
the next one is the get date.
It returns to system date in the
date time format, and it's just
select get date. and this is the
only function I think we have all
semester where we won't have an
argument of the function. So if I
just write in select get date we
leave the function empty and what
this will provide is the current
date time stamp and as you can
see it's a date time it gives the
years the hours the minutes to
seconds and then the milliseconds.
The idea of the get date is ideally
so you don't have to hardwire
in dates. Think about having
a resume and hardwiring your
age on a resume. That obviously
changes all the time, and so
this is just a dynamic way to
tackle having the current date.
Also, as a reminder, this
current date is the date on the
server, not on your computer,
and so if you're working in the
cloud, you might have to figure
out what the location of that
cloud is or what time that
they're using on a cloud device.
All right now we get into some more
sophisticated dates and this is
a powerful one and this is one
that is commonly asked on interview
questions in addition to the end of
month function. So this is the date
difference and as you can see it
gives you the difference between two
dates but there's three arguments
to the function. One is the unit
of measurement so and it is singular
day, month, year, minute, second.
So what is the difference? And
then the middle or second argument
is what is the day that you're
starting with and then you separate by
a comma and the third one is the
date that you want to compare it to
and in this case we're using get
date. So as an example here this is
me on the left hand side and my
old high school sweetheart who is a
very successful econ professor. She
was professor Harvard University
for about 10 years. On the right
hand side is my favorite image and
I will provide a link to a short
YouTube video that is narrated by
Carl Sagan. If you haven't seen it
before, this is called, I think,
the pale blue dot. And you can see
that there's kind of this sunbeam
and this little teeny dot that's
just a couple of pixels. And
as Voyager, the Voyager satellite
was traveling out of the solar
system, Carl Sagan convinced NASA
to turn the Voyager around one time
and take a photograph so this is
the the longest distance photograph
that I'm aware of uh of earth and
so that little dot is um is earth
and the picture was taken interestingly
enough in 1990 on February
14th and it's Valentine's Day and
that's why I include the photo
is uh Julie and I happened to be
in Disney World at that time and
so it was on Valentine's Day that
we were there so we can find out
excuse me we can find out how long
ago that was and let's go in and
try a date difference function now
in this case we're not going to
need a from statement because we're
providing the date but you could
certainly link a column to that how
long it's been by using columns in
the data set but we're going to use
a literal value and let's just use
the unit of time as day as day and
then it is 1990 and 0214, and if you
have a significant date and you're
following along for the blue triad,
if you would, put that in the
year you graduated from high school
or the day you graduated from high
school or some date that is important
to you, and then we'll put the
quote there, and then we'll use get
date, and on the lab or exams, if
it's asking you to write code, and
it says don't hardwire the current
date. That will indicate to use
getDate so that it's not hardwired.
And so this should be it. We have
the three arguments to the function,
the unit of time, starting
date, and ending date.
And sometimes if you get confused,
you could use the absolute
value. There is an absolute value
function, which of course, if it's
a negative number, if you got your
numbers mixed around, it would
still derive a positive number.
So it's been, wow, 13,000 days.
Yeah, that's a long time. Hi, y'all.
All right, here is your first
blue triad. And I get an email
every semester, how old, well,
when was Frankenstein born?
Well, go ahead and look that up
in Google or AI, but go ahead
if you want to pause the video
and try to solve this problem.
This will be similar to a
problem that you see on the exam.
And how you would write that code
is similar to what we just did.
Select date diff, year, and then
whatever year. This is what we
found it to be. I don't know if
that's correct. It may be when the
author was born or the book was
written or something and get date as
the minutes old. So that would be
the code to solve that problem.
All right, so now we have the year,
the month, the day, the get date,
and the date difference. And now
we'll add one more, which is also
important when we do end of month,
and that is the date add. So
there are three arguments to the
date add and that's where we can add
to a particular type of date. So
we start out with the time that we
want in terms of the measure of
time and then the distance we want
to move forward and then in this
case we're using get date but you
could put any date in there. Let
me go ahead and copy this code just
to save on time and if we put this
code in and make sure we understand
we have date add we're going to
add a months and we're going to
add months to the current date but
let's go ahead and put in an actual
date just so it'll be easier to
follow so we can indicate let's say
2030 0101 what would six months
out be from that particular date.
And you can see it would be 7
-1 of 2030. So that is great and
you can use it with different
units of time. Okay, the date
name. There are a couple of times
where you may want to have a
specific date name instead of
having, as we did earlier, remember
when we did month, and we got
the 10 for months right here.
So when we ran this, we got
a 10 or a number, but if
we don't want that number,
we can also get the name,
and there's two different kinds
that we can use, or the main
ones that differentiate. One
is mm for months, and then dw,
and I remember dw, months is easy, mm,
but dw, there's a character
in Arthur or something,
dw, And I just remembered
DW for that. If you wanted
to get the day of the week
is what that stands for.
And so if you have
output where in that case
you need to have, let's
just do a new query.
If you need to have the month show up,
we indicated the day,
so it was in February.
And then we could also change that to DW.
Go Arthur.
And that happened to be on a Wednesday.
maybe it was Bargain Wednesday
or something at Disney World, I
can't remember. Prices used to be
super cheap, now they're super
expensive. The next topic, cast, is a
great one to use with AI, with ChatGBT,
because sometimes it's difficult.
The idea of cast is if you want
to convert a data type or cast a
data type, so if you want to convert,
for instance, date-time to just
date, so get rid of those, you know,
hours, minutes, and seconds for
your output, or if you want to do
the opposite you want to add date you
want to add time here instead of
just date you can use the cast
function for that and it does have
some flexibility but you can use ai to
help you decide how that would work
best for you and there is a convert
that's also similar that we won't
discuss today but cast and convert
are very very close in terms of
their purpose so if i paste this
information in. What we currently
have is we have just the date, 2007
-02-12, and if we use the cast feature,
we could change it to this data
type, which is date time, including
the hours, minutes, and the
seconds, and this would just be the
alias that we have. So if we run this,
this should add the time to it,
and sure enough, you can see it's
no longer just a date, and we used
the cast function for that now if it
had the hours minutes seconds you
could also cast it as just a date
and not date time and it would work
as well all right we're ready for
the eo month so when i first when
i bought my first house we had this
hot tub and it had an air in it and
so we had to get fixed and for some
reason whenever after it got fixed
like every 30 seconds it would pop
up eo six which is something we'd
never forget. So you won't relate to
it as much, but EO month is how I
remember it. It's not end of month,
it's not E-month, it's EO month,
and this is the animation. I won't
play it as part of this video, but
my recommendation would be likely to
pause the video and watch the
animation and then come back, or you
could watch the rest of the video and
then watch the animation, but I think
the two together will really help
solidify your knowledge of using
the end of month, there is a lot of
power to this particular function.
If you watch the animation
on EOMonth, you're
aware that it has a lot
of power and flexibility.
At its very basic EOMonth,
you could have just
one argument, and that's
pretty straightforward.
You can have one argument here,
let me paste this over, and
if I put one argument in, and
And in this case, I'm going to
put a date in, which is kind
of fun, let's say 2030-01-05.
And it has a huge range,
past dates and future
dates, but in this case,
I can highlight this code.
And as you can see, in 2030, the
last day of the month is January
31st. We can also put that
date into a little more complex
formula where we just want the
day to show up. And so rather than
this whole date to show up, we
just want the day which would
be the 31st. So we have the EO
month and then we have the day.
We want just the day of the EO month.
And in that case we just get 31.
And of course we could use month
or year as well in order to
solve that. And in the animation,
I show a few examples of using
the second argument of the function.
So you can use EOMONTH with
just one argument, just the date
that you want to find the end of
the month. But a more powerful
use of it is you can find, for
instance, we could use GET TODAY'S
DATE and then we could add 1
to that. And what this would find
is the last day of next month.
And if we put a 2 there,
we would get the last day
of two months from now.
And if we put a negative
one there, we would get
the last day of last month.
And think about it. If you have
the last day of last month,
is it possible to use the EO
month to get the first day
of a month? And the answer
is yes. You can get the last
day of the month and then
add, use date add, and add one
day, and that would give you
the first day of the month.
All right, boo two.
Boo who? Boo two is a tough
one. So if you want to
try a tough problem, go
ahead and pause the video.
What it's asking here is this
gives you the last day of next
month using EO month. That's
great, right? We get the date,
we add one month, that'll
give us the end of next month.
But try using date add
instead and some other key
functions that you've learned
to try to find without using
the offset, try to find
the last day of next month.
Here is an example, the top
one shows it with the EO
month, but here it is without
that, we just have the
day, EO month, and then what
we're doing is date add,
we add one month, and then
we put the get date, and so
this would also give you the
last day of the next month.
That's a tough one.
Boo, try it number three.
Go ahead and pause the video
if you'd like. Show the
first day, Monday, Tuesday.
There's a character you can
think of, of the next month.
So in this case, you're using a
few of the tools that you have
available to you. In fact, I
think I have them highlighted,
the ones that you might need.
This one is also a tough one.
Here is the code for
that. Now keep in mind on
the lab, you'll have
plenty of time to practice.
So here we have the date add. we're
adding a day we're also using the
end of month so we add one day to
the end of month which would give us
the first day in that particular
case of the next month all right so
if you add the animation on end of
month which will help round out this
particular discussion you'll have
a lab on date functions with also a
few union questions but hopefully
this gives you a great start on using
date functions in your everyday
use of SQL Server, and I will see
you in a few minutes with the union
video, which will be fairly short,
will be a short video to cover that
topic. Thank you, have a good day.